A Finding Aid to the Bashka Paeff Papers, 1920-1981, in the Archives of American Art AAA.paefbash
Archives of American Art
Bashka Paeff papers
1920-1981
AAA.paefbash
Archives of American Art
1.5 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Bashka Paeff measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1981. The small collection documents her work as an artist in Boston, Massachusettes, through biographical material, two diaries, printed material, and photographs of Bashka Paeff and her artwork. Also found are an autograph book containing signatures and notes from MacDowell Colony members, one clippings scrapbook, and four photograph albums, including one from a trip to Europe in the 1920s.
Paeff, Bashka, 1894-1979
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material 1922-1981 (0.2 linear feet; Boxes 1, 3)
Series 2: Diaries, 1924-1925 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1920-1979 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Photographs, circa 1920s-1977 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Facility.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2012 by Don Richard Lipsitt, Bashka Paeff's nephew.
Biographical/Historical note
Bashka Paeff (1894-1979) was a sculptor in Boston, Massachusettes. Paeff was born in Minsk, Russia and moved to Boston with her parents when she was a year old. She studied at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, with Bela Pratt in 1914. Later she worked at the McDowell Colony and married Boston University professor Samuel M. Waxman. Paeff was known for realistic animal sculptures as well as war memorials, fountains, and portraits. Notable works include the Boy and Bird statue in the Boston Public Gardens, the Lexington Minute Men Memorial, and a statue of President Harding's pet terrier, Laddie Boy, which was cast from pennies collected by newsboys and became part of the Smithsonian Institution collection.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor Bashka Paeff measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1981. The small collection documents her work as an artist in Boston, Massachusettes, through biographical material, two diaries, printed material, and photographs of Bashka Paeff and her artwork. Also found are an autograph book containing signatures and notes from MacDowell Colony members, one clippings scrapbook, and four photograph albums, including one from a trip to Europe in the 1920s.
MacDowell Colony; Autograph albums; Diaries; Photograph albums; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--Massachusetts--Boston; Women artists--Massachusetts--Boston
- Biographical Material, 1922-1981; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1, 3
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are scattered personal papers belonging to Bashka Paeff. Included are a few cards and letters from friends; two letters regarding Paeff sent to her nephew, Donald Lipsitt; copies of Paeff's income and expense lists for much of the 1930s; and a file of press material and photographs regarding the restoration of her sculpture "Boy and Bird." Also of note is an autograph book containing signatures, notes, and poetry from friends, including other artist members of the MacDowell Colony.
  - Affidavit of Citizenship, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autograph Book, 1922-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cards and Letters to Bashka Paeff, 1965; circa 1924-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Donald Lipsitt Correspondence Regarding Bashka Paeff, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Income and Expense Lists, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Restoration of "Boy and Bird" Fountain, circa 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Award Certificate, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1924-1925; Series 2; 2 Folders Box 1
  Found here are two diaries belonging to Bashka Paeff. The diaries contain brief entries about studio work, social activites, and events in the news. The diary from 1924 only contains a few entries.
  - Diary, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, 1920-1979; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes news clippings about Paeff and other artists, pamphlets on the MacDowell colony, one exhibition catalog, and two invitations to sculpture unveilings. Also found is printed material about one of her portrait sitters Roland Hayes and a clippings scrapbook regarding her professional work in 1921.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1920-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1922-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - News Clippings Regarding Lexington Memorial, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed Material Regarding Roland Hayes, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook of Clippings, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photographs, circa 1920s-1977; Series 4; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Photographs depict Bashka Paeff in her studio and at sculpture unveilings. Also found are numerous photographs and photograph albums of her artwork, including portrait busts of men, women, and children, sculptures of animals, and public fountains and memorials. Also found are a few photographs of exhibitions of her work, her home and studio, and portraits sitters including Roland Hayes and Marian MacDowell. One photograph album includes photographs of Paeff traveling abroad with friend Juan M. Munoz.
  - Photographs of Bashka Paeff, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Photographs of Home and Studio, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions, 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Roland Hayes, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Other People, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Animals, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Children, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Men, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Various Subjects, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Women, 1920s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Negatives of Photographs of Artwork, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Photograph Album, Trip to Europe, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photograph Album, Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Album, Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album, Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Loose Photograph Album Pages, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 3-4)